<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Bohmian Rhapsody]]></title><description><![CDATA[Physics, machines & code.]]></description><link>https://sibesh.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 19:31:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[A Robot For Every Human]]></title><description><![CDATA[At MayaHQ, we’re trying to build a bot that will one day replace us – a general machine intelligence. Here is our angle of attack. ]]></description><link>https://sibesh.com/posts/a-robot-for-every-human</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sibesh.com/posts/a-robot-for-every-human</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;http://getmaya.co/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Maya&lt;/a&gt;, we’re trying to build a bot that does everything for us – a general machine intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think modern machine learning doesn’t yet have a way to do it. You can optimise it to do one thing well, so it can play superhuman Starcraft or Chess, but for generality, we need to go further – optimise generality itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental problem with current methods is that they do less from more. Feeding a lot of initial samples makes today’s bots do one narrow skill well. We want to create a process which will help build bots to do many complex tasks by rearranging the same few primitive building blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of such a more-from-less process is the language I’m using to write this. The Oxford dictionary has just 170,000 words that have evolved over years – you can reuse them to build sentences, many sentences make a paragraph and so on. Language is important because it has the symbols we use to think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To note, around 47,000 words from the Oxford Dictionary have become obsolete. This is because the natural dynamics of language are like that of a free-for-all marketplace – the useful words and phrases stay on, while the useless ones quickly slip out of use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our intuition is that a more-from-less process to making general machine intelligence should work like language does. What would this look like ? It would have, &lt;strong&gt;One&lt;/strong&gt;, a marketplace mechanism to reward the primitive building blocks and bots that work well and weed out the ones that don’t, &lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;, a domain specific language that encodes how primitives are arranged together and, &lt;strong&gt;Three&lt;/strong&gt;, a way to learn this language to auto-generate new bot flows on the go&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve the first two problems, we built Maya. The third is something we intend to figure out along the way, but we know of which there is atleast one precedent – auto-complete for the English language. &lt;strong&gt;One&lt;/strong&gt;, Maya is a marketplace that allows individuals &amp;#x26; firms to make, run &amp;#x26; sell reusable bot primitives (analogous to words) arranged to make useful bot flows (sentences), all using our cross-platform tool. &lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;, all bot flows use the Maya flow-based language to describe how different primitives are wired together. These two are hard problems on their own, but we suspect that with enough bots built using Maya and hosted on our marketplace for users to benefit from – our mission is &lt;em&gt;a bot for every human&lt;/em&gt; – we could solve problem &lt;strong&gt;Three&lt;/strong&gt; too. This would hopefully lead to a bot that “thinks ahead” (like auto-complete does) in the Maya language to generate bot flows that completes many complex tasks by rearranging the same set of primitives from the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still have a long way to go, but we think we have something interesting here. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Dangerous Intuition of David Bohm]]></title><description><![CDATA[A few months before Einstein died, he wrote about an unpopular intuition in physics which went against everything he considered sacred. An intuition surfaced by an otherwise ostracised physicist, David Bohm.]]></description><link>https://sibesh.com/posts/the-dangerous-intuition-of-david-bohm</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sibesh.com/posts/the-dangerous-intuition-of-david-bohm</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A few months before Einstein died, he wrote about an unpopular intuition in physics which went against everything he considered sacred. An intuition surfaced by an otherwise ostracised physicist, David Bohm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“[If it is true] then nothing will remain of my whole castle in the air including the theory of gravitation, but also nothing of the rest of contemporary physics.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Einstein, Bohm’s intuition was downright &lt;em&gt;dangerous&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Twitter watering-hole erupted last week when a prominent union minister dismissed mathematical figures of a lagging economy by quoting how “math never helped Einstein discover gravity”. Does math help explain the economy? Perhaps. Did math really help Einstein (re)discover his equations of gravity? David Bohm, who this essay is about, would vehemently claim that it didn’t. That would be among the very few ideas on which both Einstein and Bohm would agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this, one must first understand how a gyroscope works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to understand it is to write down the three equations that the book tells you about. Make sure angular momentum is conserved on all sides. Then mechanically derive the final result. Formulaic. Works every time. Can be taught en masse. Very &lt;em&gt;efficient.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Bohm was the kind of physicist who would never understand it that way. He would imagine himself as the gyroscope, standing on his toes, perched on a gimbal, arms stretched far, pirouetting swiftly in circles, making small muscular movements to keep his balance. He would &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; the behaviour of the gyroscope, understanding it’s motion through some form of muscular interiorization. The math and formulae would come later, almost as a pedestrian way of communicating that insight to others. Second-hand intuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bohm was a throwback to the earlier days of physics which was unusual even in his time – An era of physics devoid of reams of astronomical data, quantum supercomputers, and well-intentioned “practical” problem solving. While a Feynman would jump on any opportunity to a solve a practical problem through complicated Feynman diagrams, Bohm would actively resist formalising his intuition, letting the muscle memory of the insight simmer, evolve, and manifest in unexpected ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Dave always arrives at the right conclusions, but his mathematics is terrible. I take it home and find all sorts of errors and then have to spend the night trying to develop the correct proof. But in the end, the result is always exactly the same as the one Dave saw directly”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basil Hiley, Bohm’s colleague at Birckbeck College&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps all discovery happens this way. In the most messy, ad-hoc, inefficient manner possible, outside the sanitised corporate innovation labs. It is not surprising that when Bohm met Einstein years later, Einstein would confirm Bohm’s predilections. “&lt;em&gt;Matter&lt;/em&gt; tells &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt; how to &lt;em&gt;curve&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;curved space&lt;/em&gt; tells &lt;em&gt;matter&lt;/em&gt; how to move”, the basic principle behind his general theory of gravity, Einstein confirmed, was not arrived at by years of objective, rational thought. It was an &lt;em&gt;irrational feeling&lt;/em&gt;, a series of subtle, internal muscular sensations about four-dimensional space-time that the world didn’t yet have the mathematics to describe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This aspect of discovery doesn’t get discussed in polite company because it is impolite to attribute the profound to the irrational. There are always more convenient explanations fit for the industrialised age – like IQ, degrees, and the act of being European. How else does one justify the bizarre amnesia of high-school syllabi? Einstein’s equations explained the abnormalities in the behaviour of gravity, and predicted blackholes, and gravity waves – but this came much later. The muscular intuition came first. It is merely human to rationalise irrationality in hindsight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, this essay is not about how Einstein sympathised with Bohm, or vice versa. It is rather about the exact opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeling Causality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gary Marcus, a vocal critic of the currently most popular approach to artificial intelligence – deep learning – &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/06/opinion/ai-explainability.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; in The New York Times recently about how computer systems need to understand time, space and causality to be more..well, intelligent. What he means is that instead of learning by repetition that anything with two eyes, two ears and whiskers is a cat, it should learn that mammals have these features and hence anything with those features is a mammal, which breathes, excretes and reproduces, and a cat is just a special instance of such an mammal. Deep learning doesn’t posit an artificial intelligence to understand what &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; a cat to be a cat, and hence it is brittle, narrow and quite dumb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do human beings have intuitive understanding of how causality works? David Bohm would disagree. We have an explicitly &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; understanding of how causality works. In everyday speech, “locality” is a slightly pretentious word for a neighbourhood, town, or other place. But its original meaning, dating to the seventeenth century, is about the very concept of “place.” It means that everything has a place, a location. You can always point to an object and say, “Here it is.” If you can’t, that thing must not really exist. At any point we can localise the different features of a cat – it has ears, eyes, whiskers, and a tail. So we would want our AI to do this intuitively too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is one of the strongest intuitions of the human experience – at any point of time, we have a strong sense of place, and of the relation between spaces. We feel a strong sense of separation from those we love, and a particular kind of impotence at being unable to affect things far away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first aspect of this is “separability”. You can take four china plates and put each one in a different corner of the dining table. They will not cease to exist or lose any of their features—size, style, rigidity. The entire dining table derives its properties from the set of plates that make it up; if one hamburger can be put on each plate, then a set of four plates can serve four hamburgers. The whole is the sum of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second aspect of this intuition is “local action,” which says that objects interact only by banging into one another or recruiting some middleman to bridge the gap between them. Whenever a distance separates us from someone, we know we cannot have any effect on that person unless we cross the distance and touch, talk to, punch—somehow, make direct contact with—that person, or send someone or something to do it for us. Modern technology does not evade this principle; it merely recruits new intermediaries. A phone translates sound waves into electrical signals or radio waves that travel through wires or open space and then get translated back into sound on the other end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locality was the foundation stone on which Einstein built his castle. His theory of relativity formalises the locality we intuitively take for granted. Per Einstein, the speed of light is the cosmic limit on the speed of causality. Nothing occurs at infinite speed, and hence the world does not start and end at the same time. Places and things are “separate”, and interact via “local action”, limited by this speed limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What, then, would be the opposite of locality? So convincing is locality, that it’s opposite is simply referred to with the prefix “non” : non-locality. In the non-local picture of the universe, nothing is separate. Every particle interacts instantly with every other particle. There exists no concept of time – the universe is created and ends at the same frozen instant of time. Similarly there exists no concept of space – nothing can be separated, and while the whole may be a sum of it’s parts, there is no way for someone who is a part of the universe to localise the parts from the whole. As the joke goes, while a stitch in time would just confuse Einstein, a non-local universe would be his worst nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Bohm discovered a model of the universe consistent with all experiments, that is &lt;em&gt;explicitly non-local.&lt;/em&gt; In a book he co-wrote a few years before his death, he called it the &lt;em&gt;Undivided Universe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeling Non-Locality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We shall indulge ourselves in the absolute minutiae of math to understand what Bohmian’s idea of mechanics says. Like most good ideas, it is so horribly simple, and yet so counter-intuitive that it’s philosophical meaning has completely eluded the mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any theory of the universe can be described by how a state of set of particles is defined and how it evolves over time. In Bohmian mechanics, the state of a system of N particles (q1, q2, q3…qN) is described by its wave function ψ=ψ(&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;1,…,&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;N)=ψ(q) . The theory is then defined by two evolution equations: Schrödinger’s original equation that is basis of all of quantum mechanics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a secondary &lt;strong&gt;Guiding equation&lt;/strong&gt;, that Bohm called the pilot wave equation, that doesn’t get included any of the QM textbooks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does nobody like Bohmian mechanics? It’s predictions match up with all the other more popular interpretations of quantum mechanics, so there is no empirical reason to reject it. Most physicists say it’s because the guiding equation adds unnecessary complexity to the already elegant Schrödinger’s equation, hence it must not be required. The real reason is found in the outrageous meaning the equation makes explicit. If you look carefully, the trajectory of any particle &lt;strong&gt;“Q_k”&lt;/strong&gt;, is dependent on all other particles in the system &lt;strong&gt;(Q&lt;em&gt;1…..Q&lt;/em&gt;N)&lt;/strong&gt;, mandated by the very simultaneity of the equality sign. No time-delayed dependence, as Einstein would like it. A speed limit isn’t even required. &lt;em&gt;Explicit non-locality.&lt;/em&gt; This dangerous idea goes against every established idea in contemporary physics, and hence amounts to sacrilege, even though it is effective. This is what the above equation when applied to set of particles passing through Young’s infamous double split experiment looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the simulation in the video shows is the exact trajectories of a set of particles passing through either of two slits. The idea of determinate trajectories alone is alien to the world of mainstream quantum physics. Bohm’s equation further predicts how a quantum state deterministically collapses into a classical state. When mainstream quantum mechanics says that the choice of which slit the particle goes through is &lt;em&gt;fundamentally&lt;/em&gt; random, what Bohm says is that nothing is random – if only we knew the initial position and current position of all particles in the universe, we could simply plug it into his equation to find which slit the particle would go through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The youtube channel Veritasium, has done us all a brilliant service by creating this video about how to visualise the guiding (pilot) wave equation :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another way to intuit Bohm’s notion of an undivided universe : un-mixing drops of ink in viscous corn syrup. A hollow glass cylinder is kept inside another, and the space between is filled with viscous fluid – corn syrup. Three drops of ink are injected into the corn syrup, in a way they appear separate (“localised”) from each other. On rotating the inner cylinder, the viscous corn syrup moves in layers, layers of liquid farther away from moving cylinder stay static, the ones near it move rapidly. As a result the drops &lt;em&gt;appear&lt;/em&gt; to mix – they go from a state of less entropy to more entropy. They coalesce into a single colour, in a way it would be impossible to separate them in a traditional liquid. But corn syrup is viscous, hence on turning back the inner cylinder, the drops magically &lt;em&gt;un-mix&lt;/em&gt;, and return to their initial localised positions. Here’s a video showing how this happens:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiment is just an analogy, but it resembles how David Bohm thought about the universe. In the experiment, there exists what Bohm calls an “implicate order” (the order of colours of the separate drops) that over time evolves and mixes into this non-local mixture (where nothing is separate, everything affect everything else). Nothing in the mixture appears separate, yet it is – if the universes trajectory was rolled back, it would separate into it’s constituents in a predictable, determinate manner to reveal the “implicate order” of all the particles since an initial Big Bang event. The order Bohm speaks of is timeless, exists all the time, yet is not apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Bohm’s view, all the separate objects, entities, structures, and events in the visible or explicate world around us are relatively autonomous, stable, and temporary “sub-totalities” derived from a deeper, implicate order of unbroken wholeness. Bohm gives the analogy of a flowing stream:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this stream, one may see an ever-changing pattern of vortices, ripples, waves, splashes, etc., which evidently have no independent existence as such. Rather, they are abstracted from the flowing movement, arising and vanishing in the total process of the flow. Such transitory subsistence as may be possessed by these abstracted forms implies only a relative independence or autonomy of behaviour, rather than absolutely independent existence as ultimate substances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(David Bohm, Routledge &amp;#x26; Kegan Paul, London, Boston, 1980, p. 48.), &lt;em&gt;Wholeness and the Implicate Order&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another metaphor Bohm uses to illustrate this implicate order is that of the hologram. To make a hologram a laser light is split into two beams, one of which is reflected off an object onto a photographic plate where it interferes with the second beam. The complex swirls of the interference pattern recorded on the photographic plate appear meaningless and disordered to the naked eye. But like the ink drop dispersed in the corn syrup, the pattern possesses a hidden or &lt;em&gt;enfolde&lt;/em&gt;d order, for when illuminated with laser light it produces a three-dimensional image of the original object, which can be viewed from any angle. A remarkable feature of a hologram is that if a holographic film is cut into pieces, each piece produces an image of the whole object, though the smaller the piece the hazier the image. Clearly the form and structure of the entire object are encoded within each region of the photographic record. Bohm suggests that the whole universe can be thought of as a kind of giant, flowing hologram in which a total order is contained, in some implicit sense, in each region of space and time. When Chinese billionaire Jack Ma recently gifted a hologram gift to his employees, he would have liked to have this notion in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In perhaps the most important result in the history of quantum mechanics , John Bell in the 1960s theoretically proved through his infamous &lt;em&gt;Bell’s inequality&lt;/em&gt; that one could not accept the findings of quantum mechanics without accepting the inevitability of non-local communication. He owed his proof to a singular man – David Bohm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;… conventional formulations of quantum theory, and of quantum field theory in particular, are unprofessionally vague and ambiguous. Professional theoretical physicists ought to be able to do better. Bohm has shown us a way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J.S. Bell, &lt;em&gt;Speakable and Unspeakable in Quantum Mechanics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simulating&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Non-locality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the misgivings mainstream physics has for the explicit non-locality of Bohmian mechanics, it is used a lot in one particular domain : visualising quantum mechanics via simulation. Everything from quantum tunnelling, to decoherence and time-dependent scattering, is easily plotted and evolved using perfectly deterministic classical computers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/kvb100b/videos&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; youtube channel explores a lot of these in multicolour detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is Bohmian mechanics so useful in computer simulations of quantum mechanics? Because while non-locality might seem strange to physicists, it is not as weird to computer scientists. The scientific question of non-locality is, “How can two particles separated by half a universe be understood as connected such that they interact as though they were right on top of each other?”. If we analogise to a computer, the question would be, “How can two pictures at the far corners of the screen be understood as connected such that the distance between them is irrelevant?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the measured distance between any two pixels (dots) on the monitor’s display turns out to be entirely irrelevant, since both are merely the products of calculations carried out in the bowels of the computer as directed by the programming. The pixels may be as widely separated as you like, but the programming generating them is forever embedded in the computer’s memory in such a way that the very concept of separation in space and time of the pixels has no meaning whatsoever for the stored information, similar to Bohm’s notion of non-locality. To those familiar with functional programming, written in pseudo code, the guiding equation we encountered earlier looks like any other computer function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;type particle {
   V velocity
   X position
}

function GuidingEquation(Q_1, Q_2, Q_3....Q_N) (Q_K particle) {
     ...
     return Q_K
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above function takes in the position and velocities of ALL the particles in the computer system, and returns the position of the k-th particle. It is almost trivial to understand how the universe would evolve if it was guided by an equation like this, as opposed to something which drew explicit difference between interdependencies based on a speed limit. Whether the universe is a computer simulation or not is the unfalsifiable subject of another debate, but it certainly gives us another intuition to why non-locality may not be as strange as it appears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Echoes From a Forgotten Past&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-locality forces upon us an universe that by nature is undivided – but the concept of an undivided universe is not in itself new. Cause and effect have been important topics in all ancient schools of Indian philosophy, particularly Vedanta. All schools of Vedanta subscribe to the theory of &lt;em&gt;Satkāryavāda&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that the effect is pre-existent in the cause. Alan Watts, a prominent Eastern philosopher describes in detail the intricate concept of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Indra’s Net&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a multidimensional spider’s web in the early morning covered with dew drops. And every dew drop contains the reflection of all the other dew drops. And, in each reflected dew drop, the reflections of all the other dew drops in that reflection. And so ad infinitum. That is the Buddhist conception of the universe in an image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Watts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metaphor of Indra’s Net originates from the &lt;em&gt;Atharva Veda&lt;/em&gt; (one of the four Vedas), which likens the universe to a woven net. The net is described as being infinite, spreading in all directions with no beginning or end. At each node of the net is a jewel, so arranged that every jewel reflects all the other jewels – similar to Bohm’s hologram metaphor. No jewel exists by itself independently of the rest. Everything is related to everything else; nothing is isolated. This net describes the universe as a web of connections and interdependencies among all its members, wherein every member is both a manifestation of the whole and inseparable from the whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other texts relate this to the idea of &lt;em&gt;Brahman&lt;/em&gt; (not to be confused with &lt;em&gt;brahmin&lt;/em&gt;, which is a caste identity). Even seemingly disparate elements are described as nothing other than reflections of this &lt;em&gt;Brahman&lt;/em&gt;, and hence of one another. This notion of an organic unity – a non-locality – is a signature of Indian and most of Eastern philosophy, and distinguishes it from all major Western philosophies – that are explicitly local in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vidyāranya in his Panchadasi (V.4) explains the meaning of the phrase, or &lt;em&gt;mahavakya&lt;/em&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;Aham Brahmasmi&lt;/em&gt;“:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infinite by nature, the Supreme Self is described here by the word &lt;em&gt;Brahman&lt;/em&gt; (lit. ever expanding; the ultimate reality); the word &lt;em&gt;asmi&lt;/em&gt; denotes the identity of &lt;em&gt;aham&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Brahman&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, (the meaning of the expression &lt;em&gt;Aham Brahmasmi&lt;/em&gt; is) “I am Brahman”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bohm was astute enough to know the difference between science and &lt;em&gt;scientism&lt;/em&gt;. A communist who was literally and figuratively ostracised from America during the Cold War, and from the physics community at large, he knew that physicists harboured as much dogma as the mystic shamans. It is no surprise, that the technique of Bohmian Dialogue – which acknowledged that rigorous science and schools of philosophy both have similar goals – to arrive at an understanding of thought and reality. And so there must be a dialogue in a civilised space, reconciling differences in the absent of any judgement. His dialogues with his collaborator, Jiddu Krishnamurti, an Indian philosopher, have filled many books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is however one man’s intuition which Bohm’s notions of locality have never been reconciled with till date. A theory that was as popular as Bohm’s ideas were unpopular – Einstein’s theory of relativity. Explicit locality. Even today, the many bastions of mainstream physics reject Bohm on these grounds, as if their own vague theories of quantum mechanics are somehow perfectly consistent with relativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bringing Back the Absolute Frame&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Einstein’s theory of relativity says that the laws of physics work the same everywhere, regardless of the frame of reference i.e. (1) No frame of reference is privileged in relation to all other frames. (2) All frames of reference are privileged in relation only to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to Einstein, most scientists believed in a “luminiferous ether”, posited by Lorentz’s ether theory. The ether was an unobservable all-pervading absolute frame of reference, such that time was definitive only when at rest in that “ether” rest frame. Time in this rest frame was the yardstick that time in all other frames in motion would be relative to. They assumed that as beings on the surface of the earth traveling in the ether rest frame , our timing measurements must be distorted, although it was not possible to know by how much. Einstein’s contribution was to note that even if there were an invisible ether rest frame that we were traveling through, we could still define our inertial rest frame to have all the characteristics of a ether rest frame so that &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; timing measurements were definitive while timing measurement made at rest in the elusive ether would be distorted. In other words, it didn’t matter whether there really was an ether or not, we could define our own inertial rest frame and everything would work out just fine. In fact the idea of “Lorentzian tranformations” used by Einstein to transform event in one frame of reference to another, is borrowed from Lorentz’s ether theory, which required there to exist an absolute frame of reference in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Einstein’s approach was decidedly positivist – if scientists with PhDs couldn’t observe the ether, then it meant that it did not exist, and hence wasn’t worth bothering about. Lorentz ether theory with an absolute rest frame made the same predictions as Einstein’s special theory of relativity, it was merely another interpretation of the phenomenon described by SR. In truth, there is nothing that prevents the existence of an absolute frame of reference, except Einstein’s postulates that explicitly say otherwise. The luminiferous ether hence was as quickly forgotten as Bohm’s ideas about mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no matter of coincidence, the fundamental reason why Bohm’s notion of reality is inconsistent with Einstein’s relativity is due to the necessity of faster-than-light propagation i.e. non-locality inevitably picks out a preferred frame. The guiding wave described by Bohm’s guiding equation works non-locally in this absolute frame. This explicitly violates Einstein’s postulates. A postulate however, it should be noted, is not a divine truth, but merely an arrangement of words. There are those who believe rabidly in postulates given by men, but can an appeal to an authority that starts with an E instead of a G be really called the scientific method?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could a neo-Lorentzian ether theory of relativity that explains gravity via an absolute frame, coupled with Bohmian mechanics result in a unified theory of everything? Perhaps. It would certainly do away with the locality-non-locality debate. But we would first need to reject every epistemological notion about physics we hold, and certainly those postulates handed down by science’s favourite neighbourhood genius, Albert Einstein. If that isn’t a controversial idea, then maybe 9/11 was indeed an inside job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Delicate House Of Cards&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While critiquing Einstein is easy, it is also easy to forget that he was the first to notice the inconsistency. In his famous paper describing what is known today as the EPR paradox, he would list his problems with the inherent non-locality in quantum mechanics, or what he called “spooky-action-at-a-distance”. In so many words, his message was clear : “My intuition tells me this is wrong, and hence it is wrong(or incomplete)”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent biography of Indian freedom fighter, V.D. Savarkar, his biographer Vikram Sampath points out how Savarkar could be described as Mahatma Gandhi’s anti-christ. Not many know of the man, who saw rituals and cow worship as an abomination, advocated nuclearisation, industrialisation, militarisation and the abolishment of the caste system as the only way to develop India. Meanwhile, the Mahatma championed a rural aesthetic, the theatre of non-violence, and simple self-sustained living in the style of his many ashrams. Even today, many appropriate Gandhi to serve their own means, but looking around, India has largely gone down the way professed by Savarkar, a man deemed dangerous by both the British and the Indian establishment. Both were men of powerful intuition about what &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; right. Both are villains and heroes of different fan followings, but Savarkar is mentioned in the same breath as Gandhi precisely because his intuitions were as powerful as Gandhi’s. As Leo Tolstoy would put it – “The best stories are not between the good and the bad, but between the good and the good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albert Einstein’s intuition, the castle in the air that put locality above everything else, will perhaps attain a similar measure of piousness that Gandhi has. Bohm’s ideas too have mostly stayed outside the mainstream for mainly epistemological reasons, relegated to the elephant graveyard of physics, trying to make their way in. It is a crime of human bias, as John Bell puts it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bohm’s 1952 papers on quantum mechanics were for me a revelation. The elimination of indeterminism was very striking. But more important, it seemed to me, was the elimination of any need for a vague division of the world into “system” on the one hand, and “apparatus” or “observer” on the other. I have always felt since that people who have not grasped the ideas of those papers … and unfortunately they remain the majority … are handicapped in any discussion of the meaning of quantum mechanics. Why is the pilot wave picture ignored in textbooks? Should it not be taught, not as the only way, but as an antidote to the prevailing complacency? To show that vagueness, subjectivity, and indeterminism are not forced on us by experimental facts, but by deliberate theoretical choice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Bell&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens to men who are firmly set in muscled intuition when they come across something counter-intuitive? It burns. Like a immune system violently responding to a pathogen. Those who’ve moved past science’s most loved high-school myth, that electrons move around a sun-like nucleus in planet-like orbits have come across the usual suspects of quantum mechanics – Bohr, Schrödinger, Heisenberg et al. None of them noticed this as much as the one person whom it burned the most – Albert Einstein. He was hence the first to point it out. The first real threat to his castle in the air. David Bohm merely aggravated it from an itch to a burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes one powerful intuition to counter another. Which is perhaps why we should listen to the most dangerous ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Robots Must Be Crazy]]></title><description><![CDATA[The social currency of any self-respecting futurist-thought-leader type is to marvel publicly at how we live in an age where robots can beat us at Go, Chess and DoTA. This might be misguiding]]></description><link>https://sibesh.com/posts/the-robots-must-be-crazy</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sibesh.com/posts/the-robots-must-be-crazy</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The social currency of any self-respecting futurist-thought-leader type is to marvel publicly at how we live in an age where robots can beat us at Go, Chess and DoTA. “We live in a special time”, he repeats, for the documentary-makers in the crowd. Surely if a robot is better than the human at these, we must be close to the holy grail : artificial general intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it is also true that window cleaning robots clean windows better than humans and Roombas are absolutely superhuman at vacuuming the floor. If only the Roomba inventor had a better PR team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no, he says, it just doesn’t play complex-sounding board games – it can also recognize dogs &amp;#x26; cats, which is important, translate from Russian to English, and caption photos of things it has seen before. It’s the same neural network everywhere! Doing all these different things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course if you did create a baby with a neural network inside its head, and it became an expert at recognising cats from dogs, you would have to kill it and give birth to it again to teach it to translate Russian. The thought leader calls it “retraining with different hyper-parameters”, but we might see how a better name is “&lt;em&gt;baby-killing&lt;/em&gt;“. Mind you, not just killing babies, but also changing their sense organs to make sense of different inputs and outputs every time – like that evil kid “Sid” from Toy Story with the Frankenstein toys in his house. Given the lack of mass baby-killings it is unlikely a baby learns by this method of force feeding the same image of a cat/dog repeatedly down it’s retina (although the education system wouldn’t mind that). Do you really need to kill the baby every time? If the paper submission deadline is near, why not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we could scale it up with more compute, and more data, the thought leader further opines. After all, it took 45000 years of training on millions of dollars of compute to beat the best human at DoTA!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empirically, “victory” is an arbitrarily chosen metric that happens to tilt towards one side. It took the human David just a bowl of ramen, a cup of coffee and a few years of playing it daily to wake up and be able to evenly compete with this 45000-year superhuman Goliath. It’s a wonder he isn’t giving TED talks (yet). Should we be aiming for more compute and data or less of it? The victors write their own history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the final bogey comes : the bigger quest is to make “ethical, safe and moral” AI – the thought leader gesticulates. We must transfer all these “human” qualities to our cat-dog categorisers before it is too late. The assumption being that human beings somehow possess overflowing portions of ethics, safety and morality, in a way that tigers, polar bears and other degenerates do not. It is a way for us to feel better – this robot is better than me at everything, but surely I’m winning at morality &amp;#x26; ethics (both invented by serious-looking men without any vocation, to endlessly pontificate over trolley problems)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hands are thrown up – the thought leader has run out of parlour tricks. Well, atleast they’re trying! – he whines. Anyone trying to change the world will get hate. If we can solve this, we can solve famine, and drought, cancer and the big whopper – global warming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were all problems earlier delegated to a certain bearded Man in the clouds. One word that doesn’t come up a lot is how AGI pursuit will be immediately “useful”. How dare one make such utilitarian claims of something that holds such obvious humanitarian benefit? Just like the bearded Man, this preordained AGI providence is essentially useless until it is useful. Things that aren’t useful in the short term either die a slow painful death in the long term, or live forever as gods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;String theorists know this very well. There is no way to experimentally verify the theory’s claims. No practical applications. Which means there will never be a polite way to declare it hogwash. And so on and so forth the deliberate cycle of fund granting and thesis writing continues. Similar is deep reinforcement learning, the current shiny thing, which is without any practical use. Although that is not completely true – it makes for great headlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality of most well-funded AGI pursuits is bleak. Real environments are made artificially simpler for dumb algorithms. Horizontal ‘generalised’ mastery across tasks is sacrificed at the altar of superhuman vertical machoism that generates press. Billions of dollars of talent and compute are spent on methods completely insulated from the risks of being wrong, which any plumber/truck-driver/handyman will tell you is called bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep learning is brittle yet useful, although efforts to &lt;em&gt;generalise&lt;/em&gt; it are not. Learning is reasoning from cause to effect. As long as you’re computationally brute-forcing &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; backwards from &lt;em&gt;effect&lt;/em&gt;, which is what deep learning does, it is hard to make an intelligence that is ‘general’ and can learn on it’s own – because you cannot program all possible effect-cause pairs into it. Hence you have to retrain it from scratch to learn new things, instead of relying on it knowing a few primitive &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; to figure out all other &lt;em&gt;effects&lt;/em&gt; from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no easy solution to this, and hence it is worth working on. But not the way the thought-leaders would want it. Rather than idolising any one technology, perhaps it is better to create systems where usefulness and generalisation is explicitly incentivised by the market to improve over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I know that most men can very seldom discern even the simplest and most obvious truth if it be such as to oblige them to admit the falsity of conclusions they have formed, perhaps with much difficulty—conclusions of which they are proud, which they have taught to others, and on which they have built their lives.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leo Tolstoy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tolstoy is right, and Russian. Most thought leaders will never abandon their ways. But they can surely condemn baby-killing. It is unethical, amoral, and not very safe.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Unsettling Physics of Causality]]></title><description><![CDATA[A general relativity theorist, Bert (GR) and a quantum mechanist, Bomm (QM), find themselves in a bar that’s about to close down.]]></description><link>https://sibesh.com/posts/the-unsettling-physics-of-causality</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sibesh.com/posts/the-unsettling-physics-of-causality</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A general relativity theorist, Bert (GR) and a quantum mechanist, Bomm (QM), find themselves in a bar that’s about to close down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt;: I will allow you to talk aloud about physics, but it’s late, I’m tired, and if I have to listen to you both ramble on at 12 midnight, you have to leave out all the math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GR)&lt;/strong&gt; : Blasphemous! Understanding general relativity without Einstein’s equations is like smelling fine wine without tasting it. The beauty, the simplicity…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : And quantum mechanics doesn’t make sense outside of Schrödinger’s equations. The &lt;em&gt;wavefunction&lt;/em&gt; is all that is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender:&lt;/strong&gt; Ok, say the world is large video game working on a computer. How do I get from point A to B inside the game?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GR)&lt;/strong&gt; : That would depend on how far point A and B are. And how fast you’re travelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt; : It’s a video game. I should be able to get from point A to B at infinite speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GR)&lt;/strong&gt; : That is impossible, of course. Everything in the universe video game must have a speed upper limit. Otherwise, if things happened at infinite speeds, all observable events would happen simultaneously. There would be nothing separating cause and effect. No concept of time. All causes and and all effects would happen at once. The video game would start, and end, at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt;: Makes sense. So what’s our universe’s speed upper limit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GR)&lt;/strong&gt; : The speed of light. 300,000 km/s. That’s around a million times the speed of an airplane, which is why it might seem infinitely fast, but isn’t. Physics is all about causal interactions. A bullet leaves a gun and hits a person, the person then dies. The person can’t die BEFORE the bullet hits him. Cause and effect. The speed of light, hence, is the speed of causality – i.e. the upper limit to the speed at which things happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt; : Ah. If I’m driving on the highway and there is car on the other road travelling towards me, I see it travelling at twice my speed. If my car could travel at the speed of light, I would see the opposite car travel at twice the speed of light. Doesn’t that violate your upper limit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GM)&lt;/strong&gt; : Ah but you see, that’s where the universe is clever in how it works. There is no absolute time, or length, or velocity. i.e. there is no absolute, fixed order of causes and effects distributed in time. It’s all &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to the speed at which you’re travelling i.e. your frame of reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve heard of this one. The theory of relativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GM)&lt;/strong&gt; : So if two cars were travelling towards each other at the speed of light, time would slow down for the person sitting in both those cars, so that the order of observable events would always be restricted to the speed of light. Time would grow, and distance travelled would shrink, so the velocity (which is distance divided by time) of the two cars would appear to contract. So that if the two velocities were added, it would always be less than the speed of light. Since the ordering of cause and effect is relative to the speed at which you’re travelling, all participants – the two drivers, and also an observer standing on the side of the road – can agree on the order of observable events, even though their individual clocks don’t match. In no case, or, in no frame of reference, can a person die, before a bullet hits him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender:&lt;/strong&gt; So it’s a hack to prevent causal conflicts in the world. I could live with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GM):&lt;/strong&gt; Well, crudely put, yes. We physicists call this &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;locality&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; – local causal relativity. Local cause and effects mean cause and effect separated by the maximum speed of causality. All of Einstein’s laws of how planets move, how black holes work, how gravity works, arise from this fundamental sacred truth. General relativity, too, simply describes the geometry of causality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender:&lt;/strong&gt; I notice Bomm here has been quiet all along. Looks like he isn’t too happy with this explanation. What’s wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : Quantum mechanics is at odds with this idea. Not only is it NOT local, it is, quite unsettlingly so, &lt;em&gt;explicitly non-local.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender:&lt;/strong&gt; You mean to say that causality works faster than light? At infinite speeds?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM):&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Macroscopic objects we see around us seem to have one fixed property at a time. This tissue is white, this whisky is black . Objects at microscopic level behave differently. When isolated and until observed, they exist as a superposition of two or more possibilities – say State Black and State White, at the same time. They collapse into one when you observe them. When you bring two of them together – they entangle in an inseparable way. So inseparable, that if you took these two to opposite ends of the universe, separated them by lightyears, and then measured one of them, it would collapse into one of the possibilities. Say you observed Black. You would then see that the other atom would be White. Or if one was White, other would be in Black. Everytime. The atoms would seem to have conspired from across the universe to be exactly correlated, or anti-correlated. Spooky action-at-a-distance. Cause and effect separated by seemingly infinite speeds. Laboratory experiments have pinned this to 50,000 times the speed of light, but it could be much much higher. Infinite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender:&lt;/strong&gt; Perhaps the atoms could have conspired beforehand about which state they would collapse into, and we just can’t see how they did so?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : Ok let’s run an experiment. Say I put you and Bert in a room, and told you I would ask you both three Yes-No questions, A, B, &amp;#x26; C separately when you came out. There are two ways you could conspire to correlate answers for all 3 without me finding out – First way, you could decide before hand to always answer Yes, or No, or some combination. For 3 questions, that is 2^3, or 8 combinations. Or the Second way – when I ask you the question, you could call each other and decide on the answers you could give. Is there any other way you can think of in which to get exactly correlated answers to all three questions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt; : No, I don’t think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : So as you notice here, both the ways are strictly &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; – whether you conspire beforehand, or call each other at the time of asking, cause and effect are always separated by the speed of causality. No instantaneous communication happens at the moment I ask the questions. One could similarly think that the atoms too could have such local communication via methods hidden from us, and Yes/No answers to be Black/White. Still with me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt; : I think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bomm takes out a napkin and writes down all the possibilities for the answers to the questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://sibesh.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/Group-167x300.png%20=144x260&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : Our implicit assumption here, is locality. If we indeed do assume the first way, here are all the 8 possible combinations you could have conspired to beforehand. The fact is then, that in each pre-determined conspiracy, there are at least two questions with the same answer. If we repeated this experiment a million times, would you not say then that if we added up the frequencies of the answers being same to any two questions, the sum would be greater to or equal to one? That you would at least be assured that any two questions have the same answer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt; : Half of the possible combinations has at least two answers same, so I’d say half for any two questions chosen. And since there are three ways to choose any two questions, the maximum would be three times half, or 3/2, and the minimum would 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm&lt;/strong&gt; (QM): Correct! But experimental evidence seems to contradict this obvious result. If we repeated this experiment a million times with a pair of entangled atoms, and added up the frequencies of the answers being same to any two questions, the sum comes to hover around 3/4. Which is less than 1. Not greater than or equal to one, as our mathematical description of pre-determined strategies necessitates. A contradiction!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt; : Which means there is no way that the answers could have been pre-determined, no hidden conspiracy could have made them correlate their states exact with respect to the other?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : Precisely! And here lies the problem. The hidden pre-determined conspiracy in physics is called a theory of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;local hidden variables&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. General relativity may wear out, so might quantum theory, but there is no way to escape this statistical contradiction, this..this inequality, as John Bell put it. As long as 3/4 is not greater than or equal 1, there can be &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;local hidden variable theories&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Since locality was our only assumption, and it has been disproved, we must assume non-locality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt;: So at the moment the question is asked, the atom instantaneously communicates with it’s entangled pair, faster than the speed of light? Does that mean we can use this to boost internet speeds? Download things faster than the speed of light?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : No, I’m afraid not. While the two entangled atoms are indeed correlated across huge distances, which state one of them would collapse into is completely random. You can’t control which state one of them collapses into, and so you can’t control the other’s state. Information is about controlling the flow of 0s and 1s. Here, there is no way you can control the transfer of information at speeds faster than that of light – it would be like sending garbled random noise from one place to another. Useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender :&lt;/strong&gt; Ah so from what I understand, we have one theory of physics where everything happens at the speed of light, and another where everything happens at once. My car’s gear train is a local mechanism. Motion passes from one gear wheel to another in an unbroken chain. Break the chain by taking out a single gear and the movement cannot continue. Without something there to mediate it, a local interaction cannot cross a gap. On the other hand, the essence of non locality is unmediated action-at-a-distance. A non-local interaction jumps from body A to body B without touching anything in between. Like a voodoo doll injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm (QM)&lt;/strong&gt; : You’re picking things up really fast!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt;: However, it seems like both of you deal with difficult scales – Bert deals with large objects, and Bomm with really small ones. There’s just different laws for each. What’s to be in conflict about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert (GR) :&lt;/strong&gt; Because none of these theories put a theoretical scale at which the respective theory stops working. There is no defined line between the microscopic and the macroscopic. &lt;em&gt;Theoretically&lt;/em&gt;, quantum mechanics works at ALL scales. So does general relativity. Yet, the universe doesn’t work that way. Which means both are incomplete. They cannot be reconciled. &lt;em&gt;Yet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bartender&lt;/strong&gt; : How can two models of physics of the world be so diametrically opposite to each other? One of you swears by &lt;em&gt;locality&lt;/em&gt; and the other can’t do without &lt;em&gt;non-locality&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bert&lt;/strong&gt;: Pfft, very rich for bartenders to complain about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bomm:&lt;/strong&gt; What do you think brings us here everyday?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[This Magic Trick Has No Secrets]]></title><description><![CDATA[Ed the physicist visits a Shaman in the Himalayas to see a magic trick.]]></description><link>https://sibesh.com/posts/the-magic-trick-sans-secrets</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sibesh.com/posts/the-magic-trick-sans-secrets</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Oh great shaman, I’ve traveled far to the Himalayas to witness your magic trick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, I will show you it now. It consists of three tasks. You belong to the city – it would seem you people have short attention spans, so I will be quick. But first, take off your shoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ed takes off his shoes and the shaman takes out two boxes. He proceeds to tie both the shoes together by their shoelaces, ensuring they don’t come apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh&lt;/strong&gt; : Now wear this hood while I prepare this magic trick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ed obliges. After a while, he takes it off and sees the two boxes in from of him. His shoes are gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Your first task is to ask a question to figure out which box has both the shoes .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed (scratching head)&lt;/strong&gt; : Umm, which box has both the shoes together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman opens the left box. It has both shoes tied together. He repeats this a few times – hooding and dehooding Ed between experiments. Results are as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; This does not seem to me a very impressive magic trick. You tied my shoes together and just shift it from box to box when my hood is on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman hoods him again. He unties the shoes and separates them into two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Ok then the second task – ask a question to figure out which box has the right shoe and which the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed (getting flustered)&lt;/strong&gt;: This is ridic…okay which one has the left shoe and which one the right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman opens both the boxes to show him what’s inside each. Results are as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; We can repeat this a few times if you’re not convinced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed (getting up):&lt;/strong&gt; Oh I’m convinced all right. I’m convinced that this was a massive waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman, nonplussed, hoods him again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Now the third task. Please remove your hood and ask a question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Which question should I ask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; My friend, now you know both questions, you must choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Ok, in which box are my shoes together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman opens both the boxes to show both the shoes in one of them, tied together, the other box as empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed (a bit puzzled):&lt;/strong&gt; What if I’d chosen another question?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Why don’t you try?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hooding and dehooding happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Which box has the left shoe and which the right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman opens both the boxes, showing that each shoe is now in one of each box, now untied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed (befuddled)&lt;/strong&gt;: How did that happen? How did you know which question I was going to ask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman shakes his head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; I didn’t. Whichever question you choose to ask, is appropriately answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perplexed, Ed tries this third experiment multiple times. Every time, he sees a result appropriate to the question he asked but inappropriate to the other question he could’ve asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Surely this is unreasonable. The shoes had to be either tied together or separated right before I asked the question? What’s the trick? Hidden assistant? Some hidden compartment in the box…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman takes him inside a large cold refrigerated room. Inside is a photon beam, and two more boxes with holes, kept on top of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Here’s an atom. Its wavefunction is simultaneously in both those two boxes. A veritable Schrodinger’s cat, if you will. Do you agree this is possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed (shivering):&lt;/strong&gt; Obviously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; We now send a photon through the tiny holes in the top box. Were the atom in that box, the photon would bounce off the atom in a new direction. Were the atom in the bottom box, it would go straight through unchanged in direction. What do you think the photon would do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Since the atom is simultaneously in both boxes, the photon does both the things. The atom’s wavefunction becomes entangled with that of the photon. The parts of the atom’s wavefunction in each box would no longer by themselves be in a superposition; they would have “collapsed.” I’ve done this in a lab a bazillion times. What point are you trying to make?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; What happens next? If the photon does not interact with anything else, a tricky two-body interference experiment with this set of box pairs and photons could demonstrate that the atom was still simultaneously in both boxes — and that the photon had both bounced off the atom and gone through an empty box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Well yes, but this doesn’t explain the magic trick. I’m not leaving until you tell me the secret behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Do you not see – the result is dependent on what experiment you do! You could just look in one of the boxes, and find the atom in one of the boxes. Or do the interference experiment and find it in both. Despite your training as a physicist, do you still insist that a physical reality exists independent of your conscious observation of it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed&lt;/strong&gt;: But in this quantum experiment, the detector apparatus in interference experiment is doing the “&lt;em&gt;observing&lt;/em&gt;“, not me. Any&lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; could observe, there is no need for this consciousness mumbo-jumbo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Ah, but that is too simple an explanation. A photon coming through one of the boxes does not observe whether or not the atom is in that box. It rather joins a superposition state with the atom. Say it moves towards a detector that’s built to fire if the atom is in the top box, and not fire if it’s in the bottom one. Should the photon hit the isolated detector, being a physical system, that detector just joins the atom-photon superposition state. The detector is simultaneously fired and unfired, and the atom is still simultaneously in both boxes. Should you get a second measuring apparatus, say your eyes, to observe the detector, it too would join the superposition, for the same reasons – and so on and so forth a causal chain would be formed – a giant superposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Yet, but when I look at the detector, I see a particular result, not a superposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Exactly, but how? John von Neumann showed that the mathematics of quantum mechanics allows the collapse of the wave function to be placed at any position in the causal chain from the measurement device to the “subjective perception” of the human observer. By definition, whatever is at the end of this causal chain must collapse the wavefunction. It should also be non-physical, not satisfying Schrodinger’s equations or any physical law, otherwise, it’d also be entangled in the superposition. Some call this “consciousness”, some call it &lt;em&gt;Ātman&lt;/em&gt;, you may call it whatever you want. You may also not call it anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Ok, yes I agree, whether the atom is in superposition or not, depends on my choice of the experiment. What does my own free will specifically have to do with it? The choice of which experiment could be made by robot too. I can program a robot to take random decisions by say…flipping a coin if you will. Heads, it looks in the box; tails, it does the interference experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Agreed, you could do that. Say we had thousand such box-pairs. And say it flipped this coin a thousand times for each pair. 550 times it got head, and so the atom stayed in one of the boxes in the pair. The other 450 times it got tails, so the atom stayed in the superposition. The result, you find, is puzzling – the coin’s landing is mysteriously connected to what is there in the respective box-pair set! The robot’s supposedly random choice will strangely always be the “right” choice. This would mean that there is some direct dynamic relationship between the coin landing and the observation made – you could then conclude that the coin landing is what causes the atom’s wavefunction to collapse!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; Of course that is absurd – Bell’s theorem explicitly forbids that sort of causation. Causal relationships that travel at the speed of light, i.e. local causal relativity can never cause collapse of a wavefunction. Classical mechanics does not cause quantum phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Very good! Now, unconvinced by the theory that the landing of the coin causes the wave-function to collapse, you replace the robot’s decision making with the only decision-making process you know has nothing to with what’s going in the box-pair. What is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;My own free choice?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes! You would attach a button to the robot instructing it which experiment to do. You would direct it’s actions, it would not have any agency of its own. That brings you back into the causal chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; So what you’re saying is the world is willed into existence by my observation of it? A tree doesn’t exist when I’m not looking at it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; If there was someway to isolate a tree from local causation, like we can do conveniently for the minuscule atom, then yes it would not exist as anything other than a probability wave. But a tree doesn’t exist so, and hence your brain perceives it as a series of particles in position and time. The reason we observe only states characterized by unique positions is that we humans are beings who can experience only position (and time). Speed, for instance, is just position at two different times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; So…it might be conceivable that there could be other beings could experience reality differently? Maybe even possibly directly experience the superposition states whose existence we can only infer. I need some water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Perhaps. We can never know for sure. And it’s not just me saying it – von Neumann, Bohr, Bell, Wheeler, Wigner and a bunch of others. They and I may be wrong, but the facts are in front of you, and it is up to you to decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; You are asking me to believe that your magic trick is explained by quantum mechanics. Surely there’s trickery involved. Your demonstration involved more than an expression of conscious intent. It required you to move your hands and open the boxes. Perhaps the mechanical opening of the box pairs, either sequentially or simultaneously, somehow physically untied and put the shoes wholly in a single box or spread them over two boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh&lt;/strong&gt;: Ah but no! This magic trick has &lt;em&gt;no secrets&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing you have seen violates your laws of quantum physics. Quantum mechanics doesn’t have any restrictions on the size of the physical system. Our “technology” has merely enabled us to extend to larger objects what your Bohr of Copenhagen has taught you to accept with equanimity for the small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ed:&lt;/strong&gt; I would like my shoes back, please.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shaman looks at Ed, grinning. They go out of the room. Ed sits down to wear his shoes, bids farewell to the shaman and proceeds to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THUD&lt;/strong&gt;. Ed has collapsed, face first, flat on the ground. The shaman looks back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sh:&lt;/strong&gt; Oh, those shoelaces…&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>